Welcome back. In this video we're going to talk about finite automata
欢迎回来。在这段视频中，我们将谈论有限自动机
which we'll see in future videos are a good implementation model for regular
我们将在未来的视频中看到，这是一个很好的常规实现模型
expressions. So in the last few videos, we've been talking about regular
表情。在过去的几个视频中，我们一直在谈论常规
expressions which we use as the specification language for lexical
我们用作词法规范语言的表达式
analysis. And, in this video we're gonna start something new. We're gonna talking
分析。在这段视频中，我们将开始一些新的东西。我们要谈谈
about Finite Automata which are the For a convenience as an implementation mechanism
关于作为一种实现机制的方便的有限自动机
for regular expressions. And so regular expressions and finite automaton are very
用于正则表达式。所以正则表达式和有限自动机非常
close related. It turns out that they can specify exactly the same languages called
关系密切。事实证明，它们可以指定完全相同的语言，称为
the regular languages. We won't prove that in this course but we'll certainly make
常规语言。我们不会在本课程中证明这一点，但我们肯定会
use of that fact. So, moving right along, What is a finite automaton? Well, here is
利用这一事实。接下来，什么是有限自动机？嗯，这就是
a typical definition as you might see in a automaton theory textbook. Finite
一个典型的定义，就像你在自动机理论教科书中看到的那样。有限的
automaton consists of an input alphabet. So, it's a set of characters that it can
自动机由一个输入字母组成。所以，它是一组字符，它可以
read. It has this finite set of states. We should probably emphasize that. This is
朗读。它有这个有限的状态集。我们或许应该强调一下这一点。这是
what makes it a finite automaton is that it has some set of states that it can be
它之所以成为有限自动机，是因为它有一组它可以成为的状态
in. One of those states is special and it's designated as the start state. Some
在……里面。其中一个州是特殊的，它被指定为开始州。一些
subset of the states are accepting states so these are the states that. But, well,
这些状态的子集是接受状态，因此这些状态是。但是，好吧，
we'll just find that more in a minute but intuitively, if the automaton terminates,
我们会更直接地发现这一点，但直观地说，如果自动机终止了，
after reading some input on one of these takes that it accepts the input.
在读取其中一个镜头上的一些输入后，它将接受该输入。
Otherwise, it rejects the input and finally the automaton has some set of
否则，它会拒绝输入，最后自动机会有一些
state transitions that is in one state, they can read some input and go to another
处于一种状态的状态转换，它们可以读取一些输入并转到另一种状态
state. So let's look at that little more detail so a transition in a finite
州政府。那么让我们来看一下这个更多的细节，所以有限元数据中的一个转换
automaton. If I'm in, in this case I've written out one particular transition
机器人。如果我进去了，在这种情况下，我写下了一个特殊的过渡
here. We're in state one and we read the input A then, the automaton can move to
这里。我们处于状态1，我们读取输入A，然后，自动机可以移动到
state two, okay. And there could be lots of different transitions for the automaton
第二个州，好的。自动机可能会有很多不同的转变
from different states and different inputs and its read the following way. If we're
从不同的状态和不同的输入及其读取方式如下。如果我们
in state one on input A , we would go to state two. And, if the automaton ends in
在输入A的状态1中，我们会转到状态2。如果自动机以
an accepting state when it gets to the end of the input that is going to do what's
当它到达输入末尾时的接受状态，它将执行以下操作
called accepting the string Meaning that it will say yes, That string was in the
调用接受字符串，表示它将回答“是”，则该字符串位于
language of this machine. So intuitively the automaton starts in the start state and
此计算机的语言。因此，直观地说，自动机在启动状态下启动，
it repeatedly reads inputs one input character at a time makes a transition. So
它重复读取输入，一次一个输入字符进行转换。所以
it'll see what kind of transition it can make out of its current state based on
它将看到它可以根据以下条件对其当前状态进行哪种类型的转换
that input to another state and if that's done ringing the input it's in one of the
该输入转到另一个状态，如果该输入已完成振铃，则它处于
final states that it will accept. Otherwise is going to reject the input.
它将接受的最终状态。否则将拒绝输入。
Now, one of the situations in which it rejects, well, if it terminates In a state
现在，它拒绝的一种情况是，如果它在一种状态下终止
S, that's no one of the final or accepting states, okay? So that ends in any other
S，那不是最终的或接受的状态，好吗？所以它在任何其他地方都会结束
state besides one of the accepting states and it's going to reject. If the machine
除了其中一个接受州之外的州，它将予以拒绝。如果机器
gets stuck, Meaning it finds itself in a state and there's no transition of that
被卡住了，这意味着它发现自己处于一种状态，而不是这种状态的转换
state on the input. So in particular, let's say that in some state as a news and
输入上的状态。所以特别是，让我们说，在某些州，作为一条新闻和
the input is A, and there's no transition. There's no transition specified per state
输入是A，没有转换。没有为每个州指定转换
as an input A so the machine can't move anywhere and it get stuck and that's also
作为输入A，所以机器不能移动，它卡住了，这也是
a rejecting state. And so in these two situations, if, if you either get to the
被拒绝的状态。所以在这两种情况下，如果你到了
end of the input and it's not in a final state or. If it never reaches the end of
输入结束，并且它不处于最终状态或。如果它永远不会到达
the input because it can stuck and both of those cases it rejects the string. That
输入，因为它可能会卡住，并且这两种情况都会拒绝字符串。那
string is not in the language of the finite automaton. Now there's an
字符串不是有限自动机的语言。现在有一个
alternative notation for Finite Automata that I think is more intuitive for
有限自动机的另一种表示法，我认为它对
examples and so we're going to emphasize that way of writing the mount. In this
示例，所以我们将强调这种方式来编写坐骑。在这里面
notation a state is represented as a known graph which just draws a big circle. The
一个状态被表示为一个已知的图，它只画了一个大圆圈。这个
start state is represented as a node that has an edge or an arrow into it with no
开始状态表示为带有边或箭头的节点，其中没有
source. So, this is a transition into the node but no source node that it comes from
消息来源。因此，这是到节点的转换，但不是它所来自的源节点
and that indicates the unique start state. An accepting state is drawn as a node wit
这表明了唯一的启动状态。将接受状态绘制为具有
h just double circles like this. And finally a transition is drawn as an edge
就像这样画两个圆圈。最后，将过渡绘制为一条边
between two nodes of the graph. So with this as the time in this state that I'm
在图形的两个节点之间。所以现在是我在这个状态的时候
circling in blue and I read the input a well then I can move to this state at, at
在蓝色中圈圈，然后我读取输入，然后我可以移动到这个状态，在，
the tail of the arrow. So now, let's do a simple example. Let's try to write up the
箭头的尾巴。现在，让我们来做一个简单的例子。让我们试着写下
automaton that accepts only the single digit one. So all we need is start state.
只接受一位数的自动机。所以我们所需要的就是开始状态。
And will probably want an accepting state as well and now the questions is what do
可能也想要一个接受状态，现在的问题是做什么
we put in between the two? Well, there would be some kind of transition here and
我们把它放在这两个中间？嗯，这里会有某种形式的过渡，
it's a good guess that we should take that transition if the machine reads the one.
这是一个很好的猜测，如果机器读取了1，我们就应该进行转换。
Now let me take a moment here to talk about how the machine executes so let's
现在让我花一点时间来谈谈机器是如何执行的，所以让我们
label these states. Let's call this state a and let's call this state b, okay. So
给这些州贴上标签。让我们称这个状态为a，让我们称这个状态为b，好的。所以
the machine will have some input. Okay, and we can write that input out will be
这台机器会有一些输入。好的，我们可以把输入写成
here. So let's just say, we have the single character one and it begins in some
这里。这么说吧，我们有一个单一的字符，它开始于一些
state namely the start state. And so, one configuration of the machine is the state
状态，即开始状态。因此，机器的一种配置是状态
that it is in And the input. And typically we would indicate where it is in the input
它在里面，输入。通常，我们会指出它在输入中的位置
by just a pointers saying what position it is in the input. And, the important thing
只需一个指针就能说出它在输入中的位置。而且，重要的是
to know about input in [inaudible] the input pointer always advances. So, when
要了解[听不见]中的输入情况，输入指针总是向前移动。那么，什么时候
we, or it only advances so when we read a character input, the input pointer moves
我们或它只是前进，所以当我们读取字符输入时，输入指针会移动
to the right and it never moves back. Alright, So from state a, we have a rule.
到了右边，它就再也不会向后移动了。好的，那么从A州来看，我们有一条规则。
We can see that we're in state a. The next input character is a one and that allows
我们可以看到我们处于状态a。下一个输入字符是1，这允许
us to take a transition to state b and so now where b in state b and where as our
我们要过渡到状态b，那么现在b在状态b中的什么位置，在哪里是我们的
input point well it's beyond the end of the input indicating we are at the end of
输入点好的，它超出了输入的末尾，表明我们已经到了末尾
the input. And so now this is. We are in an accepting state and we pass the end of
输入。所以现在就是这样。我们正处于接受状态，我们已经过了
the input and so we accept. Okay? So let's, do another execution. So we start
输入，所以我们接受。好吧?所以，让我们再执行一次死刑。所以我们开始
in state a and let's take as our input the string zero. Okay. And I'd like to draw
在状态a中，让我们把字符串0作为我们的输入。好吧。我想画一幅画
the pointer. Actually I should have drawn it before the input so we'll al ways put
指针。实际上，我应该在输入之前画出来，所以我们总是会把它
the pointer between two input elements. In this case it's a merely to the left of the
两个输入元素之间的指针。在本例中，它仅位于
one we're about to read. So in this case we're about read zero so in state a. Our
一本我们即将读到的书。所以在这种情况下，我们的读数大约是零，所以在状态a。我们的
input is zero. We look at our machine. We see that there is no transition on zero.
输入为零。我们看着我们的机器。我们看到在零上没有过渡。
All right? And so the machine stays stuck. It doesn't make any move at all and this
好的?于是机器就卡住了。它一点动作都没有，而这个
is our final configuration. And we could see that we're not at the end of the input
是我们的最终配置。我们可以看到，我们不是在输入的末尾
and so this is a reject. Okay, so in this case the machine rejects that string as
所以这就是拒绝。好的，在这种情况下，机器拒绝该字符串为
not being in the language of the machine. Let's do one more example. Let's say that
没有使用机器的语言。让我们再做一个例子。我们就这么说吧
we're in state, well we're always beginning in state a and the start state,
我们处于状态，我们总是从状态a和开始状态开始，
and let's say our input this time is the string ten, okay? And our input pointer is
假设我们这次的输入是字符串10，好吗？我们的输入指针是
there. All right? So again we're in state a. The input is a one and so we'll move to
那里。好的?所以我们再一次处于状态a。输入是1，所以我们将转移到
state b. And now the input doesn't change. Just the input point changes but I'll just
状态b，现在输入不变。只是输入点发生了变化，但我只是
copy the input over to show the difference. Now the input pointer has
将输入复制过来以显示差异。现在输入指针已经
advanced cuz we've read one character of input and now we're in another state. And
高级，因为我们已经读取了输入的一个字符，现在我们处于另一个状态。和
now we can see that we're in state b. Our next input is zero and there is no
现在我们可以看到我们处于状态b。我们的下一个输入是零，没有
transition on zero from state b and so even though we're in an accepting state, b
从状态b到0的转换，所以即使我们处于接受状态
as a final state, it's one of the accept state and we haven't consumed the entire
作为最终状态，它是接受状态之一，我们没有消耗整个
input. And so this, The machine also rejects this string so this is also a
输入。所以这个，机器也会拒绝这个字符串，所以这也是一个
reject. And in general we can talk about the language. Of a finite automata that is
拒绝。一般说来，我们可以谈论语言。是一个有限自动机的集合，也就是
equal to the set of...accepted strings. Okay? So the language of a finite
等于.接受的字符串集合。好吧?所以有限定词的语言
automaton, when I'm talking about the language of a finite automaton, I mean the
自动机，当我谈论有限自动机的语言时，我的意思是
set of strings that the automaton accepts. So now let's do a more complex example.
自动机接受的一组字符串。现在让我们来做一个更复杂的例子。
Let's try to write out an automaton that accepts any number of one followed by a
让我们试着写出一个自动机，它接受任何数字的1，后跟一个
single zero. So once again well need a start state and we'll also need a final
一个零。所以我们再一次需要一个开始状态，我们还需要一个决赛
state and now let's start by thinking about what's the shortest string is that's
现在让我们先来考虑一下最短的字符串是什么
in the language of this machine. So in this case, we know it has to end in a
用这台机器的语言。所以在这种情况下，我们知道它必须以
singl e zero. So a zero definitely has to be, a zero transition has to be the last
单数为零。所以肯定必须是零，零转换必须是最后一个
move and before that zero can come any number of what? In a particular there
移动，在那个零之前可以出现任意数量的什么？在那里的一个特殊情况下
could be no 1's. So one transition in this machine is that from start state on input
可以是1。所以这台机器中的一个转换是从输入时的启动状态
zero we can definitely go to the final state because the single string consisting
我们绝对可以进入最后的状态，因为单个字符串包含
of a single zero isn't the language of this machine. And now the only question is
不是这台机器的语言。现在唯一的问题是
how do we encode the fact that any number of 1's can proceed to zero? Well, there is
我们如何编码任意数量的1都可以归零这一事实呢？嗯，有一个
an easy way to do that. We can just add a [inaudible] by the start state. And take
要做到这一点很简单。我们只需在开始状态旁添加[听不见]即可。然后拿走
that transition if we read at one. And what does this mean? This means that we'll
如果我们在一点读的话就是过渡。这意味着什么呢？这意味着我们将
stay in the state, state as longer are we're reading 1's and as soon as we read
停留在状态中，状态越长，我们读1的时间越长，一旦我们读到
zero, we'll move to the final state because that has to be the end of the
0，我们将移动到最终状态，因为那必须是
string if the machine is going to accept it. So let's do a couple of examples to
如果计算机要接受它，则为字符串。那么让我们举几个例子来说明
convince ourselves that this works. Let me label this state?s again. So this is state
说服自己这是可行的。让我再给这个州贴上标签。所以这就是州政府
a, and that's stat b. So Let's write out here states and input. So we'll begin in
这就是统计数据b，所以我们在这里写出状态和输入。所以我们要开始了
state a and let's take as input 110, okay. So let's do an accepting case first. All
声明a，让我们将其作为输入110，好的。所以让我们先做一个受理案例。全
right, So our input pointer begins to the left of the first character. So, we're in
向右，所以我们的输入指针开始于第一个字符的左侧。所以，我们加入了
state a in start state. We're reading a one and that says we should take a
状态A处于开始状态。我们在读一本书，上面说我们应该
transition that puts us back in state a. And so, we advance the input pointer. And
让我们回到状态a的转换，所以我们前进输入指针。和
now we consume the first one and, and again we're in state a and the next input
现在我们消费第一个，然后再一次处于状态a，下一个输入
is a one so we'll make another transition to state a. And the input cleaner will
是1，所以我们将再次转换到状态a。输入清理器将
advance. So now we're in state a and the next input is a zero and so we'll take the
前进。现在我们处于状态a，下一个输入是零，所以我们将
transition to b and now in this configuration, so the input pointer has
转换为b，现在在此配置中，因此输入指针具有
reached the end of the input we're in an accepting state and so the machine
到达输入的末尾时，我们处于接受状态，因此机器
accepts. 110 is in the language of this machine. So now let's do an example where
接受。110是这台机器的语言。现在让我们来做一个例子，其中
we will reject the input. And what configuration do we begin in and again a
我们将拒绝输入。我们从什么配置开始，一次又一次地
configuration for a finite automaton that just means you know a point in the
有限自动机的配置，这意味着您知道
execution it alwa ys consist of a state and a position of the, the input pointer.
它的执行还包括输入指针的状态和位置。
So our initial state is a and now let's just choose the string. I don't know,
所以我们的初始状态是a，现在让我们选择字符串。我不知道,
let's take 100 and let's confirm that this is not in the language of the machine. All
让我们取100，让我们确认这不是机器的语言。全
right, So we begin in state a and our input pointer is there. Now we read a one
好的，我们从状态a开始，我们的输入指针在那里。现在我们读一首“一”
and that means, well, you know. So it's from state a transition of one. We stay in
这意味着，嗯，你知道的。所以这是从州到州的一个转变。我们呆在家里
state a and the input pointer advances. And now we see a zero. So from state a and
状态A并且输入指针前进。现在我们看到的是零。所以从a州和
input zero, we make a transition to state b. And now the input point is here so now,
输入0，我们转换到状态b，现在输入点在这里，
we're in state b and we have an input of zero but there is no transition the b and
我们处于状态b，输入为0，但是b和b之间没有转换
zero, there are no transitions out of b at all and so the machine gets stuck, it
零，没有从b转出，所以机器卡住了，它
can't get to the en of the input and again, even though we're in an accepting
无法再一次到达输入的EN，即使我们正在接受
state we haven't read the entire input yet and so that means the machine will reject.
声明我们还没有读完整个输入，所以这意味着机器会拒绝。
And so, 100 is not in the language of this machine.
因此，100不是这台机器的语言。